[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha quite often warned people about sensuality and sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But surely this was only for celibate monks and not for lay people, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: There can't be anything inherently bad in something as beautiful as physical intimacy that you share with the person you love.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it wasn't for celibate monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if celibate monks existed as
[SPEAKER_01]: Celibate monks started to exist because of the need to give up sensuality if you wanted to practice the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like the Buddha... these two groups of people existed already, and the Buddha created a different message for each, as like different social classes or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's... he created an order of celibate monks in order to practice his teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, those are the people who actually accepted it fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody else wasn't actually a Buddhist in the full extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you can say, you know, it's beautiful and stuff, but the thing is, well, he spoke of... there is a gratification in it, in the world in general, but in centrality especially.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, if there wasn't any gratification, then certainly nobody would become attracted to things in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: But his old teaching wrote, unlike the world, and most of the things you would find in it, it doesn't stop there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It also tells you there is a danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, fortunately, there's an escape as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: While you recognize that, okay, yes, there is gratification and stuff, you also have to recognize what is it that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And unless you're lying to yourself, you would see that it also comes with fear, with concern, with the eventual crash.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether because, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like an accident, like a tragedy happened that separated you from somebody that you develop a connection with, or that person abandons you themselves out of their own choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if those two things don't happen, the fact that you are physically and emotionally connected to that person,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that you are already experiencing the burden of those possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, having something that you need to protect is already painful, even before something bad happens to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... you have to recognize that with that physical bond comes an emotional bond as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And anybody who says otherwise is just lying to themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you cannot not emotionally care and be concerned and and not be affected by the loss of somebody that you have had physical intimacy with or that you expect to have physical intimacy with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's automatic that you will care about that person and you will suffer if something happens to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you couldn't help it, then, sure, you could say, like, choose wisely, like, who you get together with, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, you do have a choice, because, as I said just before, there is an escape, which is, if that danger became sufficiently apparent, you would lose desire for sexuality and sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it works the same as with anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you were in the habit of playing with vipers your whole life, since you were a kid, it might seem unthinkable to you, in that you would abstain from it, or lose desire for it, because it's habitual.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, at the same time, you recognize that it's just a principle of the mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: That the only way you can do something is if you think that the benefit is greater than the harm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that is flipped, it doesn't matter what... how many times you did it before, that activity will become impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing that you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generally seeing more of a harm than a benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if... even if it's
[SPEAKER_01]: You do it because you see... either you don't see the harm at all, or you perceive the harm as being lesser than the benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you dwell on that harm, then because it is actually there, in the same way as the gratification is actually there, it's objectively there,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will lose desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because it's on the same universal footing, the fact that certain things are agreeable, certain things are beautiful, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the same universal level that, to the extent that you have desire for those things, you have this bond that is like constantly having repercussions.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sense of filling you with concern, filling you with tension.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... you need to have, like, this faith, to some extent, the same faith that an addict would need to have, to realize that without his condition of addiction, he would be better off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if he isn't honest, he could easily justify himself into thinking that, you know, mental gymnastics himself into thinking that it's kind of inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be that better anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's going to be the same either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not worth abandoning the addiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to see a problem with the state in which you're currently in, and you need to have some amount of faith that you can resolve it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, pretty soon, you start to see that actually, at least part of the desire is optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, it's... you can't
[SPEAKER_01]: And as a result of keeping the precepts, reflecting on danger, you can start to see that it starts to go down, which already shows you, like, well, that that is at least partial evidence that it is possible to overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would see, like, even if you could never overcome it completely, which is not true, but let's say hypothetically, every grain of it you would have, you were worse off on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would still be better off by decreasing it to the to the greatest extent possible, because you would be decreasing... it's like decreasing the amount of weight that you're carrying in a backpack.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, it's just because you're used to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only gratification you know is the sensual one.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels to you like life starts there, and everything else is kind of optional, but this is the constant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, all of this, the light in sensuality, is something that you could be without.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, like, you can see how it increased, most likely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can see how it wasn't as bad as it is now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you could see how, in the past, it was more, now it is less, for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see that, actually, this is not constant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is, most certainly,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it would be a sign as well of overcoming sensuality rightly or practicing towards it when you dwell on the benefit that it gives you, even if you would stop right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you said, you overcome a little grain of sensuality and even if you can't go any further for whatever reason, because it's not possible or you can't do it, you're factually better off than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't... Like, the Buddhist teaching is to abandon all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the Buddhist teaching is that craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in line with the Buddhist teaching, all sensuality is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's still, like... it's still up to you, in the sense that
[SPEAKER_01]: And the good news is that you don't change that perspective, that you don't adopt the view that some of the sensuality that you're giving into is justified.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you will... then, at least, you are in the ballpark of the Buddhist teaching, and you will
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like I said just now, if it is clear that the harm of something outweighs the benefit, you can't possibly have a favorable attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be trying to get more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might see yourself as, like, being weak and unable to to live up to your own ideals, but your ideals would be that sensuality, clearly, you would see for yourself, is, like the Buddha said, a charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a concrete statement of the effect it has on your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like a religious
[SPEAKER_01]: mechanistic influence of how desiring essential pleasure burns you internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see that, like, you could take an instance where you don't have desire for something, and there is, like, some
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a hypothetical benefit in it to be had, but you don't find yourself having desire for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, like, and let's say there's a hypothetical benefit, but then also a very clear harm that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you know, a very powerful drug that kills you in a few years, but it will give you, like, the best trips that you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would see, like, yes, that is a factual benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless you were already addicted, almost everyone would say no to that, because from where they're standing, it's clear that even though there is a gratification, the harm outweighs it, because you don't want to die in a few years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, for everybody who is subjected to sensual
[SPEAKER_01]: Difficult doesn't mean mandatory.
[SPEAKER_01]: Difficult to overcome doesn't mean mandatory.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just because of not realizing, like, wait, I actually have an option not to die in a few years, and I'm choosing to forsake it, that you would, eh... not think... just not thinking about it, not reflecting on it, you would just continue living as normal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's that... it's that, eh... again, even when everything is perfectly fine,
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you delight in sensual pleasure has this huge weight behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you may not get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when after you got it, you may not get enough of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you're having it, other people might compromise it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It may, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: There are just so many variables that are between you and that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's only by ignoring that entire scope of tribulation that comes with it, that you would think, oh yeah, this is actually worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a modern simile actually for the whole charcoal pit leper
[SPEAKER_00]: Story would be a drug addict.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because we don't have this these days anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, most people probably don't even know what leprosy is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we probably don't have any disease that comes close to it, in terms of, as well, the treatment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, having this kind of super painful treatment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe cancer and the kind of these kind of cocktails that you get.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no, like, impulsive behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, the drug would be, because the drug is, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You really... you do it only because you... it's very painful not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're free from that addiction, you would never go back to, like, you know, taking the drug.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you would realize that the immense contrast between being free from it and
[SPEAKER_01]: Where not doing it is very unpleasant, which is basically what distorts your perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: It biases you, because it's just a natural human bias that things that are inconvenient or difficult, you want to write them off as not necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that bias was gone, for whatever reason,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the case of sensuality, it would have to be that you became the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even with the drug, like, let's say you just magically were... something happened that just made you not an addict anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You actually had the option not to give in to the drug.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be clear to you, like, how you were, like, the entire doom, trajectory towards doom that you're bringing yourself to,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is what frees you from desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha would say, the sensual pleasures are... they're painful, they're much... provide much despair, and the peril there is what is greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the sense of maybe where the, actually, the addiction analogy is much better as well, that to overcome an addiction, you need to change your whole way of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might need to move, change the district, change your friends, change the people you associate with, because everything was based on that addiction, that you get the stuff, that you have easy access to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, I think, for a leper, I'm not sure how that... Yeah, yes, it's... especially when the... yeah, the things that gain their meaning or their significance to you because of the addiction, you would only be implicitly having a favorable attitude towards the addiction by keeping them around.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, certain friends, certain... like when the Buddha talked about bad friendship,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like actively criminal, sort of very very bad people under every circumstance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just people who have values that oppose dhamma, which is anybody who doesn't see a problem with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start reflecting on that danger for yourself, because you have to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't be
[SPEAKER_01]: Operating, again, just based on religious zealotism, being like, oh, yeah, the Buddha said that it's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you actually believe in it and you have faith in him and stuff, but the desire will only fade if you clearly, for yourself, see, like, even if I was the last person on this planet and nobody would judge me on account of it, the charcoal pit doesn't go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: For myself, like, how my mind will be afflicted, if I were to delight in this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start cultivating that perception, actually, then, naturally, you will start inclining away from certain environments and certain people, but the thing is, eh... usually, like, you have to do it the other way around, because
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to develop the perception of danger sufficiently, or it won't sink in sufficiently enough, because you're acting out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, because you're still actively reinforcing the priority of the gratification through your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still seeing that as, as, eh... like training yourself, and seeing that as more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there has to be a, eh... an extent of
[SPEAKER_01]: Where even if the withdrawal symptoms of the drug are still there, you're still not consuming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't expect that you will, like, think and reflect and clarify, and then suddenly, I won't feel like consuming the drug, and then I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to plan for, usually, a very great deal of resistance of, like, I want to take it, but I decided I won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you distance yourself from certain environments, certain people, that for you were engaged with only for the sake of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start keeping the precepts, and whenever that desire comes up, you reflect on that danger, and you clarify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if it feels pointless,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the thing is, you're not trying to figure out a theory, because it's not a very complicated subject.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about a hidden kind of, you know, how the pieces come together or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one fact, simple fact, that you just don't want to think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, simply by thinking about it, reminding yourself of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: The same fact, that's the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to deepen your... the complexity of your theory about the danger of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's to not stop reminding yourself of that simple fact, that the burn, the pain of the desire, how it simply feels in your mind, is never
[SPEAKER_01]: That always outweighs the impact of any pleasure that you could get by acting while that burn is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, rather than putting the pleasure, the gratification first, you put the danger first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but you see the danger as the burn that is already present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a
[SPEAKER_01]: Something that comes later.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like when the bad things happen, because then you could theorize that, oh, well, if I just handle all the variables well enough, I could hypothetically have sensuality without danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The simple delight is the danger because of the burn that it implies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the burn and the uncertainty and
[SPEAKER_01]: All of the... it puts you in this vulnerable position, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that vulnerability, in and of itself, is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would never choose it, if you saw that that's worse than the... or that that outweighs the gratification.